Part 2: How to prevent mucositis.
As you start radiation,
we would like for you to do
a set of rinses to help prevent mucositis.
The first thing we ask
is that you do this specific regimen
that involves both baking soda and MuGard.
Baking Soda: Rinse and spit.
We would like for you
to take a teaspoon of baking soda
and mix it with eight ounces of water.
You will then rinse your mouth
for one minute and then spit it out.
Do not swallow the baking soda.
Mugard: Rinse and Swallow.
Immediately after the baking soda rinse,
we would like you to take a mouthful,
5 to 10ml of MuGard and rinse your mouth
for 30 seconds and then swallow it.
The MuGard will not only protect your mouth,
but it will also help protect your throat
and esophagus during treatment.
The MuGard may not taste so pleasant,
but it is well worth the benefits
and protection from radiation.
We will provide you a
bottle of the Mugard sample
on the first day of radiation.
If you do not receive one.
Please ask our nursing staff.
We will also write you a prescription
for  MuGard
that will be sent to your home.
You may receive a call
from an out of state pharmacy,
which is a specialty pharmacy
that will be asking you
for information
on where to send your MuGard to.
Please be sure to answer this call.
Lastly, please be sure to do both baking
soda and MuGard every day
at least twice a day.
Your doctor may ask you to do it
more often, up to 4 to 5 times a day,
especially if the mucositis is present
or worsening.
We may also ask you to take a Q-Tip
and apply extra Mugard to the areas
of mucositis, the specific white
spots on your tongue or mouth.
If you do not have MuGard,
please do not continue baking soda alone.
Baking soda should only be done
right before the MuGard.